[SPEAKER_00]: So, I've got a passage from a sutta, Majjhima Nikaya, 48, Kosambi Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the end of it, the last few paragraphs.
[SPEAKER_00]: I thought it was quite a nice description of the understanding of the Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I thought it might be something to talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's after the bit where the Buddha's talking about what leads to friendliness, cordiality, and bhikkhus, and saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says these six things lead to... if, you know, engaging these six things, the saṅgha will be harmonious, unity, living in concord.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the last one is having the right view, sharing the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says that's the peak, that's the most... That's the fundamental one.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the fundamental one, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is sort of secondary to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then he says, and how, Bhikkhus, does this view, which is noble, leading on, lead whoever acts on this, on, towards the correct destruction of suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Here bhikkhus, a bhikkhu gone to the forest, or gone to the root of a tree, or gone to an empty dwelling, reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there any internal obsession unabandoned by me, because of which, with this obsession, I can't understand, I can't see the essence of the obsessed mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: If bhikkhus, a bhikkhu is obsessed by the passion of sense desire, there's just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If Bhikkhu is obsessed by ill-will, there is just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If a Bhikkhu is obsessed by sloth and torpor, tiredness and sluggishness, there is just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he's obsessed by agitation and remorse, it's just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he's obsessed by doubt, there's just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If Abhikkhu is engaged in thoughts about this world, it's just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If Abhikkhu is engaged in thoughts about another world, it's just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If Abhikkhu is involved in quarrels, disputes, having fallen into an argument, dwells stabbing others with verbal daggers, there is just an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: There isn't any internal obsession, unabandoned by me,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of which, this obsession, with this obsession, I can't understand, I can't see the essence of the obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mind is well-directed for the awakening of truths, of the truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: For him, this first knowledge is attained, which is noble, world-transcendent, not shared by cotuginous.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what all those things have in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: Things as in of the obsessions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, all the... doubt is an obsession, your world is an obsession, charity is an obsession, thinking about this world is an obsession, the other world is an obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's all mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all mind, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... and that's... that's... so, it says there clearly, it's not... he chases down and analyzes doubt, chases down, analyzes centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, he just knows this results in obsession of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obsession is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows obsession as obsession being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means understanding of the nature of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nature of it, not the content of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the experience of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why this special experience, this...
[SPEAKER_01]: Out-of-this-world experience, not-out-of-this-world experience, experience-of, free-from-lust, with-lust, all of that, is secondary to the mind being first, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding the nature of that mind means surmounting anything that can obsess that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he talks there about these different obsessions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is that for each one, this is just an example of an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what they have in common that's the most important thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop trying to discern and analyze the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just see it as an example of the nature behind it that you want to discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, only then will you know, will you be able to answer for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right now, there is an obsessed mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know what an obsessed mind is... Well, otherwise, it's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your obsessed mind is determined by presence of greed, aversion, delusion, or thoughts of this world, it means you will be affected when those things are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you develop your mind so when obsession of... when ill-will is present, the mind is not obsessed by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ill-will is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The content is still the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the mind is now not obsessed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you've understood that whether there's an obsessed mind or an unobsessed mind... Because, basically, you refrain from entertaining the further obsession towards the content and you force yourself to look for the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you stop chasing down the individual experiences and start understanding them universally.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because obsession does not... it requires maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It requires your involvement.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it requires you to choose, basically, to feed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like when people know, like, you know that, or at least you have the idea, that suffering is caused by craving, not by adverse circumstances you experience in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you experience the adverse, like, say, somebody comes and says something upsetting to you, so you know that on a theoretical level, you suffer because of your craving, not because of what they said.
[SPEAKER_01]: But on practical level, you can't restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you still go after that person or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot help yourself but be obsessed about the content that upsets you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, same when you meet agreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: The prospect of sensuality, you know, the excitement, you are not developed in regard to it, you cannot help but be obsessed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you choose to give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, that's why, like we... in so many talks, like, sense restraint is not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to be a sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to develop that sense restraint to the point that you are able to see the nature of whatever's presently in front of you, in terms of the content of your experience,
[SPEAKER_01]: And not be obsessed by it, and not go after it, and not be pulled by saying yes, or repelled by saying no.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sense-restraint, another way of sort of describing sense-restraint, would be refusing, not acting out of obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of obsession.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good obsession or bad obsession, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obsession is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in order to do that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sense-restraint outlines your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which then gets you to discern what obsession actually is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems to be like you're talking about cittanimitta, seeing... Yeah, the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the necessary, as the Buddha said, prerequisite for sotāpati, for the right view, is to develop sign of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: To see the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means able to, like, transcend the presently enduring content that's pulling you, pushing you, upsetting you, obsessing you, and you still see beyond it, in terms of the mind that endures there simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, which is what...
[SPEAKER_00]: All of these different types of mind have in common.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's, like, it just seems to be that's one, that's one knowledge that, eh, it says, like, a sotāpanna can ask himself, he ponders, he thinks, okay, can I
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I aware of the presence of obsessed mind or non-obsessed mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how, by being unable to be obsessed, even amidst obsessing circumstances, obsessing content, that's how you become unable to suffer, even amidst suffering, as Buddha said, which begins with sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you ask yourself,
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I free from suffering in that sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I not suffer even while I'm experiencing that which is suffering, that which is disagreeable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would my mind remain unobsessed by it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or would I fear it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I incline away from it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I try to shelter myself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I try to protect myself?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those attitudes still imply that you think suffering is there, so you're protecting yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't think it would... a practitioner wouldn't be able to conceive of that question being asked.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if transparent, Patlujana probably could.
[SPEAKER_01]: The one that's not avoiding responsibility or mystifying the content of his experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, it's not only... this doesn't only refer to things that are unpleasant in their nature, that obsess your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It refers to things that are pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chasing novelty experience, chasing those meditation releases, all of that is focused on the content of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you're completely unaware of the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unaware of the nature means unaware of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unaware of the mind, there is no prerequisite for the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how special your experience might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I was saying before, like that whole, like eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Overly affirming or overly denying attitude towards the content of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same when we mention in our talks when people have mystical experience and it's really, it's not the experience that's mystical, it's their attitude that mystifies it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any experience is just an experience, just the content of the senses or the mind as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's your attitude whether mystifies, whether glorifies and values the content in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's mystical.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not what you... but if... see, for as long as you value what you experience or what you want or what you might, to that extent, you value the view of the content of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't matter what you experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is whether the mind is obsessed by it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can only...
[SPEAKER_00]: Not be obsessed by it, or affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by learning how to deal with content perfectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you don't want to be free from suffering, you will be free from suffering, because that's the automatic result of seeing the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot suffer, because suffering requires an obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to then do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Furthermore, bhikkhus, a noble disciple reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's funny that in the previous one, he just said a bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, bhikkhu is a bhikkhu gone to the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, the rest of these samajas are all about a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_00]: He reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pursuing, developing, making much of this view, do I gain calm, samatha, for myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I gain extinguishment of myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pursuing, developing, making much of this view, I gain calm for myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: I gain extinguishment of myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbhuti.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's just further verifying exactly what you already know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already know that this view, this way of regarding things,
[SPEAKER_01]: It frees you from obsessions, which implies inability to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I pursue that view, oh, then the further calm comes out of it, and then the further extinguishment of anything else, in terms of views and habits that were rooted upon greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the second knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, furthermore, a noble disciple reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as I'm endowed with this view, are there any other ascetics or brahmins outside here endowed with such a view?
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as I'm endowed with this view, there aren't any other ascetics and brahmins outside here endowed with this view.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to arrive at that view is to understand it correctly, which is only found within the Buddha's instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see what that says?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what that implies is
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible to stumble upon it spontaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, eh... accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when, like the... before the Buddha, like Pacheco Buddha, even they don't stumble upon it spontaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: They recognize the value of their development, they pursue it, and they free their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense that Sammasambuddha did.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's another, eh... sort of, eh... clear indication of how you... why you should not be chasing your... your experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if a spiritual nature... Because they're just... Because they happen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding doesn't happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop it in regard to things that happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for as long as you value things happening to you, you will not be understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either in the content or you're refraining from valuing the content and looking at the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Furthermore, Anobha Dissalpa reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as an individual who has attained the right view is endowed with a nature, usually it's like with a character, with a body, you know, he has a particular nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I endowed with such a nature?
[SPEAKER_00]: In what way, and in what way because an individual who has attained the right view endowed with such a nature?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the nature of an individual who has attained the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though such a one falls into an offense, such that the rehabilitation from that offense is known, still he quickly indicates, discloses, clarifies to a teacher or to his wise companions in the holy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having indicated, disclosed, clarified, he undergoes restraint in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: That means that the utmost personal things, personal wrongdoings, cannot be taken as personal anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He discloses it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason people don't disclose things is because of the involvement of their conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fear or whatever, but it's all rooted in sense of I am in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Self-view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Self-worth that comes out of the self-view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for somebody with the right view, it's... he's incapable of taking it personally, even things that resulted like wrongdoings out of still remnants of his personality.
[SPEAKER_01]: His greed, his aversion, his delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he's unable to take it personally, on that fundamental level, to not disclose it, or not see it as a... oh, that was a wrong doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you... if you... if you recognize you've done something wrong, and then you have this...
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of looking for excuses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you start covering up, start making it opaque and non-transparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's impossible for a person with the right view, layperson or a monk, doesn't matter, to become opaque again and lie to himself about his own motives or doings or actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, there's the simile basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just because, just as a little young boy, a baby, having stepped on burning coal with his hand or foot, quickly moves back, in just this way, because this is the nature of an individual who's attained right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though he falls into a fancy quickly, discloses, indicates, sort of immediately.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the first reaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's nothing getting in the way of him, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: Covering it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Covering it up, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for him, this is the fourth knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: This fourth knowledge is attained, which is noble, beyond the world, shared, not shared by patujanas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Furthermore, bhikkhus, a noble disciple reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as an individual who's attained the right view is endowed with a nature, am I endowed with such a nature?
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's the same, same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, eh... Bhikkhus, this is the nature of an individual who has attained the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though he has become active in terms of various duties with his companions in the holy life, there's still a keen regard for training in the higher virtue, for training in the higher mind, for training in the higher understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, just as a cow eats the grass with her young calf, and she watches over her young calf, in just this way, bhikkhus, this is the nature of every individual who's taken the right view, even though he has become active, in terms of various duties, he doesn't give up training.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't lose the context, despite the other more mundane things he might have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: We cannot forget the context of the right view, and the implicit development in it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the very
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be ignored.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even like back in the suttas, where lay people became sotāpānas and then kind of chose to continue living their household life.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's something they cannot forget.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, throughout their life, they always start... but basically, after the right view, they would have felt
[SPEAKER_01]: At least a degree of discrepancy between the value of the right view and development and what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also an obstacle, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It says that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an obstacle in that's in Udana.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha says...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think in Udana it says the noble disciple will sort of not progress because fondness for work, talk and sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's in the aggregate kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah, maybe I'm wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is
[SPEAKER_00]: Work, yeah, will... an obstacle for a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and why, like, in other sutras, like, you might wonder, well, how would somebody who's so dependent not pursue further?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't feel you don't have... you don't feel like you have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other people might be, like, some people might be satisfied with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you cannot suffer amid suffering, and everything else is literally seven grains of sand left.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know, you know that there are mountains or Himalayas, that's how much you've done already.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, oh, this is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's nothing from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they would have said, even that little is still something, so that's why you should do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But some monks or lay people would have just been content with that and which would have allowed them to live the life which cannot be aligned with the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Lay life cannot be aligned with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you chose to stay a layman or as a bhikkhu, sometimes, you chose to basically not really practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's against the right view and you have to live that discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Live like a layman in clothes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would feel that discrepancy and sooner or later, you would have to basically... you would turn away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you're saying here is...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you're doing that... Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a noble disciple, you can't forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's like the right view inclines towards nibbāna, slopes towards... that's its natural direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... now you've established that, and you cannot not incline that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says, at most, seven lifetimes, at most, you will have to go in nibbāna by the end of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is another, again, another... And that's the only reason, by the way, why Sotāpanna would sometimes take seven lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they're not practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even with the utmost non-practice, within seven items, you would have to basically drain any interest towards anything that's that's discrepant with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not compatible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even if you're not practicing, and you're not behaving, you're behaving in a way that's sort of contradicting your understanding, you still understand, you still have this knowledge, you still... Oh, yeah, that's... you cannot lose that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reflect, you go... Because... and you know why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not given to you like a random special experience that happened and you don't know how or why.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you understood the nature of anything that arises for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, whatever has the nature of arising, that's why that nature is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the always the the inside of sotāpanna and the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not when this special thing arose for me, I became Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's understanding that whatever is of a nature to manifest, that's why it cannot be mine, because it has manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like in this case, it began with the nature of the mind, recognizing the nature of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and that understanding of that manifestation is on the level of the mind, yeah, not on the level of the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: Furthermore, a noble disciple reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just quite like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just these, you know, it's about these things that the noble disciple thinks about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as an individual who has attained the right view is endowed with strength,
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I endowed with such strength?
[SPEAKER_00]: And in what way bhikkhus is an individual who has attained the right view endowed with such strength?
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, this is the strength of an individual who has attained the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever has been made known by the tathāgata in this dhamma and discipline, while it's being taught, having heeded the meaning, having attended, having collected together with the whole mind, lending an ear, he listens to the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands in this way, just as an individual has attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He listens to the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't like... Well, he cannot... it doesn't take effort for him to listen to the dhamma, because his experience now has been aligned with the universal principle of the dhamma, through his understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever he comes across the dhamma, it's immediately that strength is there, that direct connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even that is not personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, let me make the effort and think about the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when he listens to the dhamma, it's basically just he gets reminded of what's already within his experience seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, again, the next one's similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just as an individual who has attained the right view is endowed with strength, am I endowed with such strength?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the strength?
[SPEAKER_00]: The strength of an individual who has attained right view is this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever has been made known by the Tathāgata in this dhamma discipline, while it's being taught, he... so I've translated this as he gets an experience of the meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: He gets an experience of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: He attains joy associated with the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it's being said, even if he doesn't think about the dhamma, what's being heard is what he experiences as a direct description of what he is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also why a Sotāpanna will be able to tell whether somebody has the right view or not, or whether somebody talks... what somebody said is aligned with the right view or not, even if it's not coming from the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody makes a statement, he will be able to tell whether that statement is accurate or not, whether it's true or false.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on the direct experience of the meaning of that statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Pali there is Atavada and Atavada and Dhammavada... Ataveda and Dhammaveda.
[SPEAKER_00]: And usually it's translated as kind of some spirit... religious joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the... No, it's more like a universal joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, it might be joy, but it... You know, like, when you understood something for yourself, and then you see it in the world understood by others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That already provides you with joy, even on a mundane level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone on a level of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And somebody talks about freedom from suffering, you cannot not be joyous about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's universal, it's beyond you, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be taken personally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, even the joy you get from it, it's beyond your personality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why it's a joy that's
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to be feared, and it's to be cultivated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing wrong with that joy, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, like, people get... experience joy when they find somebody else sharing their central preference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, saying tasty music, or whatever, they get that... Wow!
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine... Oh, yeah, that band's great, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine how much more, when you find somebody also talking about freedom from suffering, exactly how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a joy you can't crave for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because craving requires obsession, requires personality, requires basically lack of that sight of your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Endowed in this way, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Endowed in this way, with the seven factors, the nature of a noble disciple has been properly considered for the realization of the fruit of stream-entry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, endowed in this way, with seven factors, a noble disciple is endowed with the fruit of stream-entry.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems to me it's like the... it's a description of the kind of authentic questioning that a sotāpanna
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, but it all starts with that thorough, transparent, wisely considered sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, it doesn't matter if you wear robes or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to discern the obsessed mind as obsessed mind, you need to discern what mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be able to withstand
[SPEAKER_01]: the content of experience that has manifested for you, that is pulling you, pushing you, distracting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through denying the content, but through restraining the loss of perspective through your action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you choose to act out of the content, you forsake the perspective towards the content.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason why a lay person is less likely to become a sotāpanna today is because they would need to endure more pain because of the environment they are in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't endure the pain of sensory strain because of the sensory strain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You endure the pain because of the bombardment of that which you are restrained against.
[SPEAKER_01]: And today's lay environment is far more proliferated with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if sensory strain is impossible, it's only because they can't bear enough pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, the only way to learn how to bear pain is to start bearing the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's too much, well, you have an option.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either forsake the value of sensory strain, in which case, you've forsaken the value of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, if you say you're practicing the dhamma, you're not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you could then, maybe, change the environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can't become a monk or a nun to the point that you can really change the environment that will suit and enable you at least to bear some pain of that sensory strain without being overwhelmed by it, well, then find find something in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: At least withdraw yourself to some extent and then you'll see how much you can bear.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know how much you can bear if you never try to bear it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're still acting out of obsessions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards, against, both towards and against, confusion, obsession of doubt, all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you, say, a person is able to withstand the sensory strain, to then reflect upon, like, motivation behind your thoughts, speech and actions, because when I'm... in the previous talk we mentioned sensory state, it's not just precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts are
[SPEAKER_01]: Clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what you don't do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, sensory strain comes within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, do I need to look at this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not for the sake of saying no to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not look.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not sit.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just wanting to know why.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is this rooted at?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it rooted in obsession?
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, do I feel pressured to act towards this?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already a form of obsession.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the nature of the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: By discerning that obsession is the underlying cause for your action, you will then learn how to not act when you're not obsessed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you... and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, how to not act when you are... when obsessed, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you're not obsessed... How to act.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you can act freely.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that... that comfort of knowing it doesn't matter, requires you understand...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through learning about obsession as an underlying motivation, you get to discern the signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to become a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regards to motivation of your action is necessary, enduring the obsession is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enduring the obsession and developing strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, like in this...
[SPEAKER_01]: It forces you into strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, am I strong enough?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have the strength of somebody who is...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If not, then I have to develop my strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you endure obsession by not acting towards what obsesses you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not giving in to the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just enduring the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... and that can also be a reflection itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Spend your entire day thinking or keeping a corner of your eye at your mind to see whether you're acting out of obsession or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'm sitting here talking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I obsessed with this?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, do I feel pressure on account of this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do I feel I need to act or avoid or... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, it might change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I feel like I must say all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so now you're obsessed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't act out of obsession.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all about, oh, I will say this, I will not say... No, just don't act out of obsession.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't do that, whatever you say will not be wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't that another way of describing the practice of sensuous driving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah, yeah, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like another way of thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I'm not acting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just recognize when obsession is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not going to act out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obsession.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contact.